{"tossups": [{"question": "In this decade, Irving Ives was defeated in a gubernatorial race by W. Averell Harriman, who later lost a Democratic nomination in this decade to a man who campaigned on the \u201cNew Politics\u201d platform. Both presidential elections during this decade resulted in the victor using a West Point Bible during his inauguration which followed losing campaigns by a Democratic governor of Illinois. For ten points, name this decade in which Adlai Stevenson was twice defeated for president by Dwight Eisenhower.", "answer": "<em><b> 1950</b></em>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A character in this film creates a jingle to the tune of \u201cDokdo is our land,\u201d a patriotic song about the disputed Liancourt Rocks to remember that she is an only child from Chicago. In this film, a woman asks for tables to be arranged in a \u201ccrane\u2019s wing\u201d formation to emulate Admiral Yi at the Battle of Hansan Island. This film is the first fully non-English film to win a Best Picture Oscar. For ten points, name this 2019 Korean film by Bong Joon-ho about a poor family that infiltrates a rich household.", "answer": "<em><b> Parasite</b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "Gabriel Nicolas de la Reynie is generally considered the founder of these modern organizations that take their name from the Greek for \u201ccitizenship.\u201d One of these organizations replaced London\u2019s watchmen. That organization was created by Sir Robert Peel, and its members were known as Bobbies. Under Napoleon, vagabonds and deserters were among those surveilled by, for ten points, what type of organization, empowered to enforce the law and capture criminals?", "answer": "<em><b> Police</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The longest-serving holder of this position gained the nickname \u201cKing Dick.\u201d Another holder of this position named John Hall proposed that one Chinese immigrant could enter the country for every 10 pounds of cargo. While holding this position, David Lange made his country a nuclear-free zone. The first successful Anglophone effort for women\u2019s suffrage occurred while Richard Seddon held this position. For ten points, name this office held by Helen Clark and Jacinda Ardern.", "answer": "<em><b> Prime Minister</b></em> of<em><b> New Zealand</b></em> (accept<em><b> PM</b></em> of<em><b> New Zealand</b></em>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "When this city was attacked, John Rabe created a safety zone to protect civilians from invading soldiers. This city was the capital of Wang Jingwei\u2019s puppet government. This city was the first capital of the Ming Dynasty, and it also served in that role for the Taiping Kingdom and the Kuomintang. This city names the first \u201cunequal treaty\u201d which ended the First Opium War. For ten points, name this city where a namesake \u201cRape\u201d occurred during the Second Sino-Japanese War.", "answer": "<em><b> Nanjing</b></em> (accept<em><b> Nanking</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man spelled out the word \u201chetacomb\u201d in a speech that began, \u201cWhat we\u2019re going to try to do, is we\u2019re going to try to rap and educate.\u201d Howard Alk directed a documentary about this man\u2019s murder. This man coined the phrase \u201crainbow coalition\u201d in 1969. Along with Mark Clark, this man was killed in his sleep during a Chicago Police Department raid. The Weather Underground declared war on the government after the death of, for ten points, what Black Panther leader from Illinois?", "answer": "Fred(rick)<em><b> Hampton</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The person named to this position in 2014 authored the book Hit Refresh. Another holder of this position cited high costs when he said of their competitor, \u201cThere\u2019s no chance that the iPhone is going to get any significant market share.\u201d Steve Ballmer held this position from 2000 to 2014, succeeding a Harvard dropout who, with Warren Buffett, founded The Giving Pledge. For ten points, Bill Gates held what leadership position at a company that created the Windows operating system?", "answer": "<em><b> C</b></em>hief<em><b> E</b></em>xecutive<em><b> O</b></em>fficer of<em><b> Microsoft</b></em> (prompt on answers such as \u201cHead of Microsoft\u201d, do not accept or prompt on \u201cpresident of Microsoft\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A man with this profession was venerated by the Rosicrucians for his allegedly prophetic\u201cprognostications.\u201d That member of this profession may have been calling himself superior to a Roman practitioner when he named himself \u201cParacelsus.\u201d Henry II of France was served by a member of this profession named Ambrose Pare, the first to describe phantom limb pain. For ten points, name this profession whose medieval practitioners followed Galen\u2019s theory of the four humors.", "answer": "<em><b> Doctor</b></em>(s) (accept any answer indicating the medical profession)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This book claims that before coinage, people risked \u201cthe grossest frauds and impositions\u201d if they failed to carefully consider purchases. Many of this book\u2019s ideas originated in its author\u2019s earlier Theory of Moral Sentiments. This book used the example of a pin factory to illustrate the division of labor and posited the existence of an invisible hand. For ten points, name this book of laissez-faire economics written by Adam Smith.", "answer": "An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the<em><b> Wealth of Nations</b></em>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "This man vetoed the Bland-Allison Act in order to preserve the gold standard. This man sent Federal troops to guard railway installations, breaking the Great Railroad Strike. Although he supported black male suffrage, this man was forced to withdraw federal troops from the South in order to become president following a disputed election against Samuel Tilden. For ten points, name this Republican from Ohio who became president as a result of the Compromise of 1877.", "answer": "Rutherford B(irchard)<em><b> Hayes</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This war\u2019s European campaign included French defeats at the Battles of Minden, Villinghausen, Krefeld, and Rossbach. This war\u2019s Indian campaign, also called the Third Carnatic War, included a French defeat at Plassey and the later loss of Pondicherry in 1761. This war\u2019s American theater featured French defeats at Signal Hill in Newfoundland and at the Plains of Abraham outside Quebec City. For ten points, name this war fought between 1756 and 1763 and named for its length?", "answer": "<em><b> Seven Years\u2019</b></em> War (do not accept \u201cFrench and Indian War\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The stability-instability hypothesis argues that these objects reduce major conflicts but increase minor ones. The Russell-Einstein manifesto opposed these objects, whose use Robert McNamara argued would lead to \u201cmutually assured destruction.\u201d Fears of a retaliatory \u201csecond strike\u201d led advocates of deterrence theory to build, but not use, these weapons. For ten points, name these weapons of mass destruction that were dropped on Nagasaki and Hiroshima.", "answer": "<em><b> Nuclear weapon</b></em>s (accept any specific type, such as<em><b> nuclear bomb</b></em>,<em><b> atomic bomb</b></em>, etc.)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s presidency, the longest-serving cabinet member in U.S. history, Secretary of Agriculture James Wilson, began his post. This man\u2019s successor said this man had the \u201cmoral backbone of a chocolate eclair.\u201d Mark Hanna was the power-broker for this man\u2019s \u201cfront-porch\u201d campaign conducted from his home in Canton. Leon Czolgosz [CHOW-gaw] assassinated this president at the Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo. For ten points, name this president who was succeeded by Theodore Roosevelt.", "answer": "William<em><b> McKinley</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This A leader of this region gave the \u201cShawinigan Handshake\u201d chokehold to a protester in 1996. This region experienced a \u201cGreat Darkness\u201d during its rule by a conservative, anti-government premier in the 1940s. Jean Lesage and Robert Bourassa led this province\u2019s Quiet Revolution. This region passed the controversial Bill 101 in 1977 to establish its official language. A pair of referenda in the 1990s concerned the independence of, for ten points, what Francophone Canadian province?", "answer": "<em><b> Quebec</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Juan de Ayala named several features in this body of water that he was the first European to pass through. Mariano Vallejo named a county along this body of water after the Miwok chief Marin. A similar, smaller body of water to this body\u2019s south was named in honor of the Conde de Monterrey. An island in this body of water was given a name translating from Spanish as \u201cisland of the pelicans,\u201d and is today known as Alcatraz. For ten points, name this body of water that is connected to the Pacific by the Golden Gate.", "answer": "<em><b> San Francisco Bay</b></em>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The Marquis de Condorcet gave himself away as an aristocrat during this period by ordering an omelette. During this period, the first Levee en masse military conscription of 18 to 25 year olds was levied by the government. This period included the deaths of Marat by assassination and the fall of the Committee of Public Safety after the Thermidorian Reaction. For ten points, name this violent period during the French Revolution that included the death of many of the enemies of Robespierre.", "answer": "<em><b> Reign of Terror</b></em> (prompt on \u201cFrench Revolution\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Waltzes by a composer from this country make up pianist Dinu Lipatti\u2019s most enduring recording. In 1887, a minuet in G was written by a man who later signed the Treaty of Versailles as this country\u2019s prime minister. Arthur Rubinstein is best known for recording pieces by a composer from this country who wrote four Ballades. That composer from this country wrote the Revolutionary Etude after the November Uprising in this country. For ten points, name this home country of Frederic Chopin, who wrote many mazurkas.", "answer": "<em><b> Poland</b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "At this building in 1954, four Puerto Rican nationalists including Lolita Lebron committed an armed attack. The original Charles Bulfinch dome on this location was replaced by a \u201cwedding-cake style\u201d dome, on which the \u201cStatue of Freedom\u201d stands and where The Apotheosis of Washington was painted. Partially burned in the War of 1812, Benjamin Latrobe was an architect of this landmark. For ten points, name this building, home of the U.S. Congress.", "answer": "United States<em><b> Capitol</b></em> Building", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Queen Elizabeth I visited this location in 2007 and declared this site the \u201cbeginning...of the British Empire.\u201d This location was the destination of a Christopher Newport-led relief effort until the Sea Venture was wrecked off the coast of (+) Bermuda during the \u201cThird Supply.\u201d This location was saved from a harsh winter by the arrival of Thomas West, Baron De La Warr. This location faced the (*)</b> \u201cStarving Time\u201d in the same year one of its leaders proclaimed, \u201cHe who does not work, neither shall he eat.\u201d John Smith helped lead, for ten points, what first permanent English settlement in North America?", "answer": "<em><b> Jamestown</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In one work by this author, vice president-elect Domino Caycedo and Simon Bolivar discuss passports so the latter can leave the country. This author wrote about the murder of Santiago Nasar by the Vicario twins in (+) Chronicle of a Death Foretold and fictionalized a massacre in Cienaga that was carried out by the United Fruit Company in The General in his Labyrinth. In 2014, Juan Manuel Santos called this man \u201cthe greatest (*)</b> Colombian who ever lived.\u201d For ten points, name this author who wrote about the Buendia family in One Hundred Years of Solitude.", "answer": "Gabriel (\u201dGabo\u201d or \u201cGabito\u201d)<em><b> Garcia Marquez</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>This ruler enforced justice through the establishment of 12-man thegn [THANE] boards at Wantage. This man became an economic vassal after Byrhtnoth was defeated at the Battle of (+) Maldon. This ruler ordered the St. Brice\u2019s Day Massacre, prompting Thorkell the Tall and Sweyn Forkbeard to attack his kingdom. This father of Edward the Confessor paid the first (*)</b> Danegeld in order to buy off Viking invaders. For ten points, name this English king whose epithet is incorrectly translated into modern English and is more correctly understood as \u201cpoorly advised\u201d rather than \u201cill-prepared.\u201d", "answer": "<em><b> Aethelred the Unready</b></em> (accept<em><b> Aethelred II</b></em> )", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The tanegashima is a Japanese device that is powered by this substance, which was originally produced with bitterwort. The Song Dynasty era text Wujing Zongyao contains the first (+) chemical composition of this substance. The Daoist alchemical text Zhenyuan miaodao yaolue contains one of the earliest references to this substance. The Ottoman, Safavid and Mughal empires can attribute their initial (*)</b> dominance to the use of this substance. The original Chinese word for this substance means \u201cfire medicine.\u201d For ten points, name this explosive substance made of saltpeter, sulfur, and charcoal.", "answer": "<em><b> Gunpowder</b></em> (accept<em><b> black powder</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Tuskegee Institute director Julius Rosenwald invested in one of these businesses along with Henry Goldman. While attempting to turn around one of these businesses, Chicago businessman Sewell Avery fought the FDR administration who (+) forcefully seized the company. John Wanamaker founded the first business of this type in Philadelphia with the motto \u201cone price, all (*) </b> goods returnable.\u201d Montgomery Ward was the first American one of these businesses and gave customers its \u201cWish Book.\u201d People ordered goods through catalogs from, for ten points, what businesses such as Sears?", "answer": "<em><b> Department store</b></em>s (prompt on \u201cretail\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This thinker\u2019s main theological works are gathered in a series of Upbuilding Discourses and were published after his death as his \u201csecond publication.\u201d This thinker examined the claims of a \u201cteleological suspension of the ethical\u201d in another work, which described (+) Abraham\u2019s attempted sacrifice of Isaac. This thinker criticized Christendom in \u201cThe Corsair Affair\u201d and attacked the state-supported Church of (*) </b> Denmark as contrary to the idea that\u201cChristianity is the individual.\u201d For ten points, name this Danish theologian and philosopher who wrote Either/Or.", "answer": "Soren<em><b> Kierkegaard</b></em>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>This uprising achieved initial success when government troops fled under the impact of a Highlander charge at the Battle of Prestonpans. The Skye Boat Song commemorates the escape of the instigator of this uprising while (+) disguised as a maid and aided by Flora MacDonald. In the last pitched battle fought on British soil, the Duke of Cumberland defeated this uprising at the Battle of (*) </b> Culloden [cuh-LAH-dun]. For ten points, name this unsuccessful rebellion launched by Bonnie Prince Charlie that attempted to restore the Stuart family to the British throne.", "answer": "<em><b> Jacobite rising</b></em> of 17<em><b>45</b></em> (accept<em><b> \u201845 rebellion</b></em> or<em><b> the \u201845</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>After being injured by a cannonball during a battle in this decade, Thomas Pasley legendarily said \u201cThank you, but never mind my leg: take care of my flag\u201dwhile serving as first commander of the Bellerophon. The (+) Glorious First of June occurred during this decade. Near the end of this decade, the ammunition of a ship named the Orient exploded, contributing to a victory for (*)</b> Horatio Nelson. The Battle of the Nile was fought near the end of this decade and contributed to the start of the War of the Second Coalition. For ten points, name this decade that began the French Revolutionary Wars.", "answer": "<em><b> 1790s</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}